Register of the Edward B. Marks Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Edward B. Marks papers
1932-2005
2006C55
Marks, Edward B.
6 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs and other writings, correspondence, reports, printed matter, and photographs, relating to international assistance to refugees from World War II to the 1980s.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Edward B. Marks was an American refugee worker who worked as an official with the U.S. War Relocation Authority, the International Refugee Organization, and the International Organization for Migration, as well as the U.S. Committee for Refugees, the U.S. Agency for International Development, and UNICEF from the 1940s to the 1980s.
Scope and Content of Collection
Contains materials relating to international assistance to refugees from World War II through the 1980s, documentation on the various refugee organizations Marks worked for or with over the same years, photographs documenting the United States Agency for International Development and the United Nations. Printed matter, writings and speeches document refugee experiences from all over the world, the International Year of the Child in 1979, the United Nations, and Marks' memoirs.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Refugees.; International relief.; United States. War Relocation Authority.; International Refugee Organization.; International Organization for Migration.; U.S. Committee for Refugees.; United States. Agency for International Development.; UNICEF.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1932-2002 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by format
  - Awards, Lester Granger Award, 2001-2002 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings about E. B. Marks, 1944-1967 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Correspondence (Folder 1)
    - Family, 1937-1966 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Miscellaneous organizations, 1938-1962 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Speaking engagements file, 1939-1960 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Travels file (Folder 1)
    - Germany and the U.S.S.R., 1932 (Folder 1: 6)
    - U.S.S.R., 1978 (Folder 1: 7)
- Organizations file, 1932-2001 (Box 1-3)
  Arranged alphabetically by the name of organization
  - Association of Former International Civil Servants (AFICS), 1996-2001 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Atlas Publishing Company (Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Publications, American Wine and Liquor Journal, July 1935 (edited by E. B. Marks) (Folder 1: 10)
    - Research material on temperance movement, 1936-1991 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Statements from E. B. Marks regarding labor dispute, 1938 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Immigration and Refugee Services of America, 2001 (Folder 1: 13)
  - International Committee on European Migration, proposed television program, "Nation on Nations,", 1956 (Folder 1: 13)
  - International Film Associates, 1946 (Folder 1: 14)
  - United Nations (Folder 1-2)
    - General (Folder 1)
      - Clippings, 2001-2003 (Folder 1: 15)
      - Correspondence (Folder 1)
        - Ferrero-Waldner, Benita, 1995 (Folder 1: 16)
        - Ogata, Sadako, 1991 (Folder 1: 17)
        - Vieira de Mello, Sergio, 1991 (Folder 1: 18)
      - Identification badge, undated (Folder 1: 19)
    - High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR), notes, 1994 (Folder 1: 20)
    - International Year of the Child (Folder 1-2)
      - Clippings, 1978-1980 (Folder 1: 21)
      - Conferences (Folder 1)
        - Lists of, 1978-1979 (Folder 1: 22)
        - Paper, "Child Advocacy in the Century of the Child," Catherine Ross, 1979 (Folder 1: 23)
      - Correspondence, 1979 (Folder 1: 24)
      - Grun, John (Director of Secretariat), 1980 (Folder 1: 25)
      - Memoranda, 1980-1981 (Folder 1: 26)
      - Miscellaneous, 1979 (Folder 1: 27)
      - Publications (Folder 1)
        - "IYC Report,", January 1979 (Folder 1: 28)
        - "Pictures from a Small Planet,", 1980 (Folder 1: 29)
      - Publicity (Folder 1)
        - "Childquotes about Children,", 1978 (Folder 1: 30)
        - Draft plan and letter, 1978 (Folder 1: 31)
      - Reports (Folder 1-2)
        - "Epilogue, The Impact of the Year," by E. B. Marks, undated (Folder 1: 32)
        - "Highlights of National Action in IYC,", 1981 (Folder 1: 33)
        - "International Year of the Child, Report to the President," U.S. National Commission, 1980 (Folder 2: 1)
        - "Principal United Nations Documents and Resolutions Pertaining to IYC,", 1981 (Folder 2: 2)
        - "Studies on Children Produced in or as a Result of IYC,", 1981 (Folder 2: 3)
        - Untitled, about the role of non-governmental organizations in IYC, 1981 (Folder 2: 4)
      - Signage and logos, undated (Folder 2: 5)
    - International Year of Peace, draft memorandum by E. B. Marks, 1984 (Folder 2: 6)
    - UNICEF (Folder 2)
      - "A Brief History of the U.S. Committee for UNICEF," by C. Lloyd Bailey, 1981 (Folder 2: 7)
      - Clippings, 1988-1990 (Folder 2: 8)
      - Colleagues, 1987-1996 (Folder 2: 9)
      - Convention on the Rights of the Child, 1988-1989 (Folder 2: 10)
      - Correspondence, Downs, Hugh, 1990-1996 (Folder 2: 11)
      - Executive Board Reports (Folder 2)
        - "Children in Eastern Europe, an Information Note,", 1990 (Folder 2: 12)
        - "Progress Report on the International Child Development Centre,", 1990 (Folder 2: 13)
        - "Report of the Executive Director, Overview of Actions for Children in 1989,", 1990 (Folder 2: 14)
        - "Statement by James Grant, Executive Director...at opening of Executive Board session, May 1980" (Folder 2: 15)
      - Non-Governmental Organizations Committee on UNICEF, 1982 (Folder 2: 16)
      - Publications, miscellaneous, 1988-1990 (Folder 2: 17)
      - World Summit for Children, 1989-1990 (Folder 2: 18)
    - United Nations Association: Talking points on accomplishments of United Nations, undated (Folder 2: 19)
    - Years project, 1984 (Folder 2: 20)
  - U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) (Folder 2)
    - Bureau for Africa, 1963-1965 (Folder 2: 21)
    - Business card, undated (Folder 2: 22)
    - Correspondence, 1966; 1976 (Folder 2: 23)
    - Distinguished Service Award, 1976 (Folder 2: 24)
    - Report, "Operations Babylift,", 1975 (Folder 2: 25)
    - Responses to criticism of foreign aid, 1963-1965 (Folder 2: 26)
    - Vietnamese refugee camps, 1965 (Folder 2: 26)
    - Background information (Folder 2)
      - Clippings (Folder 2)
        - 1942-1943 (Folder 2: 28)
        - 1980-2002 (Folder 2: 29)
        - Redress issue, 1983-1987 (Folder 2: 30)
        - Resignation of Harold Ickes, 1946 (Folder 2: 31)
      - National Refugee Service Special Information Bulletins, 1942 (Folder 2: 32)
      - Pamphlet from Home Missions Council, 1942 (Folder 2: 33)
      - Reprint of article, Far Eastern Survey, 1942 (Folder 2: 34)
      - Stafford Press (Stafford School, Minidoka Relocation Center), undated; circa 1945 (Folder 2: 35)
      - "Study of Immigration and Naturalization Laws and Problems," Hearings, U.S. House Committee on Immigration and Naturalization, 1945 (Folder 2: 36)
    - Correspondence about (Folder 2)
      - Riesman, David, 1989 (Folder 2: 37)
      - Robinson, Greg, 1999 (Folder 2: 38)
    - Eulogy for Dillon S. Myer, by E. B. Marks, 1982 (Folder 2: 39)
    - Guidelines on Community Activities, 1943 (Folder 2: 40)
    - Memoranda and reports, 1942-1945 (Folder 2: 41)
    - Notes by E. B. Marks, 1942-1943 (Folder 2: 42)
    - Publications, 1942-1943 (Folder 3)
      - WRA: A Story of Human Conservation (unattributed but largely written by E. B. Marks), 1946 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Published articles about WRA, 1998-1999 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Response to exhibit "America's Concentration Camps,", 1998-2000 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Welfare Council of New York City (Folder 3)
    - Memoranda, 1938 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Organization chart, 1936 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Publications, Better Times (Folder 3)
      - 1936-1938 (Folder 3: 6)
      - 1939 (Folder 3: 7)
    - Publicity (Folder 3: 8)
- Speeches and writings, 1935-2005 (Box 3-4: 8)
  Arranged chronologically
  - List, undated (Folder 3: 9)
  - Miscellaneous autobiographical fragments, undated (Folder 3: 10)
  - Poetry, humorous, undated (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Wanted: A Change in New York's Wine Laws," New York Times Magazine, January 1935 (Folder 3: 12)
  - "The Drys Crusade Again, With New Tactics," New York Times Magazine, 1936 October 25 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Proposal for a Sunday welfare page, sent to New York Times, December 1936 (Folder 3: 14)
  - "The Federal Theatre and the Consumer," paper for course at Columbia University, April 1938 (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Youth Groups and the Newcomers-A Symposium," The Youth Leader, October-November 1940 (Folder 3: 16)
  - "Star-Spangled Showmen: The Dilemma of the Federal Theatre," Masters thesis, Columbia University, 1939 (Folder 3)
    - Background information, 1938-1940 (Folder 3: 17)
    - Notes, undated (Folder 3: 18)
    - Drafts of text, undated, around 1938-1939 (Folder 3: 19)
  - "The Volunteer in Auxiliary Services with Refugees," The Jewish Social Service Quarterly, September 1941 (Folder 3: 20)
  - "Token Shipment: The Story of America's War Refugee Shelter" (Washington: War Relocation Authority, 1946) (Folder 4: 1)
  - "Fair Exchange," The American Magazine, June 1946 (Folder 4: 2)
  - "The Hard Core DP's," The Survey, June 1946 (Folder 4: 3)
  - "Migration in Transition," notes on immigrant care, July 1955 (Folder 4: 4)
  - "Millions on the Move," Public Welfare, July 1956 (Folder 4: 5)
  - "Internationally Assisted Migration: ICEM Rounds Out Five Years of Resettlement," International Organization, Volume XI, Number 3, 1957 (Folder 4: 6)
  - "Planned Migration, 1956-1957: A Report," Common Council for American Unity, May 22, 1957 (Folder 4: 7)
  - "How the Yugoslav Camps for Hungarian Refugees Were Closed," Migration News, November-December 1958 (Folder 4: 8)
  - "The Cuban Refugee Dilemma," unpublished typescript, March 1962 (Folder 4: 9)
  - "Refugees in Three Areas: Plight of the Uprooted Chinese, Africans, Cubans," unpublished report, July 1962 (Folder 4: 10)
  - "Saigon: The Impact on the Refugees," The Reporter, January 12, 1967 (Folder 4: 11)
  - "Child Abuse," speech at Yale University conference, 1979 (Folder 4: 12)
  - "Why an International Year of the Child?" speech given by E. B. Marks on several occasions as Associate Director for IYC Secretariat, 1979 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Notes for various speeches, International Year of the Child, 1979 (Folder 4: 14)
  - "The Year of the Child," undated chapter draft of untitled work (Folder 4: 15)
  - Untitled book proposal, for work about refugees, circa 1980 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Untitled fragments about refugees, circa 1980 (Folder 4: 17)
  - "Anti-Maim," undated satirical poem about gun control, circa 1980 (Folder 4: 18)
  - "American Attitudes and Policies," unpublished typescript about refugees, circa 1983 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Untitled summary of Marks' experiences in refugee resettlement, circa 1984 (Folder 4: 20)
  - "10.6 Million Refugees Face an Erosion of World Concern," unpublished typescript, 1984 (Folder 4: 21)
  - "Refugees and the American Ethic," unpublished typescript, circa 1986 (Folder 4: 22)
  - "People in Limbo," unpublished typescript, circa 1989 (Folder 4: 23)
  - "The Refugees Are on the Move, and the Rich Countries Can Help," Philadelphia Inquirer, undated, circa 1989 (Folder 4: 24)
  - "Bonjour Boyesse: A Memoir of Wartime Saigon," unpublished typescript, circa 1990 (Folder 4: 25)
  - "An Upper West Side Story," undated typescript, circa 1990 (Folder 4: 26)
  - "For a Better World: Posters from the United Nations" (San Francisco: Pomegranate Press, 2000), correspondence, 1992-2000 (Folder 4: 27)
  - "American Corporations Help Vietnamese Educators to Improve Teaching of English," typescript submitted to Boston Globe, 1998 (Folder 4: 28)
  - "Art...at Home in the United Nations," United Nations Chronicle, No. 4, 1998 (Folder 4: 29)
  - "The Tortuous Path to Citizenship," unpublished typescript, 1998 (Folder 4: 30)
  - "Talk on U.N. Day," speech notes, 2002 (Folder 4: 31)
  - "Still Counting: Achievements and Follies of a Nonagenarian" (Lanham, MD: Hamilton Books, 2005) (Folder 4: 32)
- Photographs, 1948-2000 (Box 5)
  - United Nations International Refugee Organization, Geneva and Athens, 1948-1953 (Folder 5: 1)
  - United States Agency for International Development (Folder 5)
    - Refugee camps in South Vietnam, 1965 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Congressional delegation visit, 1965 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Refugee camps in South Vietnam, circa 1965-1966 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Nigeria, circa 1969-1970 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Unidentified (perhaps India or Bangladesh), 1975 (Folder 5: 6)
    - E. B. Marks receiving Distinguished Service Award, 1976 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Trip to Soviet Union, 1978 (Folder 5: 8)
  - United Nations (Folder 5)
    - Photographs from International Labor Organization, circa 1979 (Folder 5: 9)
    - Photographs for book, "A World of Art,", 1989 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Photographs for book, "For a Better World,", 2000 (Folder 5: 11)
- Printed matter, 1939-1995 (Box 5-6)
  Arranged alphabetically by title
  - "America and the Refugees," by Louis Adamic (Public Affairs Committee, 1939) (Folder 5: 12)
  - "America Meets the Refugee: A Handbook on the Program of the National Refugee Service, Inc." (New York: National Refugee Service, 1940) (Folder 5: 13)
  - "American Voluntary Aid for Germany, 1945-1950," by Edward McSweeney, O.P. (Freiburg i.B.: Caritasverlag, 1950) (Folder 5: 14)
  - "American Voluntary Aid for Germany, 1945-1950," by Edward McSweeney, O.P. (Freiburg i.B.: Caritasverlag, 1950) (Folder 5: 15)
  - "Don't Fence Me In!: Fort Ontario Refugees and How They Won Their Freedom," by Joseph H. Smart (Salt Lake City: Heritage Arts, 1991) (Folder 5: 16)
  - "The Émigré Physician in America, 1941," reprinted from the Journal of the American Medical Association, November 29, 1941 (Folder 6: 1)
  - "Fridtjof Nansen," by Chr. A.R. Christensen (U.N. High Commission for Refugees, et.al., 1961) (Folder 6: 2)
  - "Immigrants and Refugees: Their Similarities, Differences, and Needs," International Committee for European Migration, 1976 (Folder 6: 3)
  - "In Her Own Words," by Helenka Adamowska Pantaleoni (New York: U.S. Commission for UNICEF, 1994) (Folder 6: 4)
  - "The International Committee for World Refugee Year, 1959-1961," ICWRY (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Paths to the New World," by Edward Corsi, (New York: Anti Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1953) (Folder 6: 6)
  - "The Problem of Chinese Refugees in Hong Kong: Report Submitted to the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees," by Dr. Edvard Hambro, 1954 (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Protestant Experience with United States Immigration, 1910-1960," by Benson Y. Landis (Church World Service, 1961) (Folder 6: 8)
  - "Refugees in Philadelphia," Philadelphia Study Committee on Refugee Integration, 1962 (Folder 6: 9)
  - "The Stranger at Our Gate," by Hubert H. Humphrey, Jr. (New York: Public Affairs Committee, 1954) (Folder 6: 10)
  - "The String Bracelet: Reflections of and by the Young People of Southeast Asia," compiled by Kyle Farmbry (Washington DC: Intercultural Productions, 1989) (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Teaching About International Organizations," by Gene M. Lyons (Academic Council on the United Nations System, 1988) (Folder 6: 12)
  - "The United Nations: Fifty Years After San Francisco," by Edward C. Luck and Gene M. Lyons (Hanover, N.H.: Dickey Center, Dartmouth College, 1995) (Folder 6: 13)
  - "We Strangers and Afraid," by Elfan Rees (New York: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1959) (Folder 6: 14)